<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is built from a template for a generic Internet Draft. Suggestions for
     improvement welcome - write to Brian Carpenter, brian.e.carpenter @ gmail.com -->

<!-- This can be converted using the Web service at http://xml.resource.org/experimental.html
     (which supports the latest, sometimes undocumented and under-tested, features.) -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [


]>


<?rfc toc="yes"?>            <!-- You want a table of contents -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>        <!-- Use symbolic labels for references -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>       <!-- This sorts the references -->
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>    <!-- Change to "yes" if someone has disclosed IPR for the draft -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>


<!-- This defines the specific filename and version number of your draft (and inserts the appropriate IETF boilerplate -->
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-bogdanovic-netmod-yang-model-classification-01" category="info"  >


<front>
  <title abbrev="YANG model classification">YANG model classification</title>

  <author fullname="Dean Bogdanovic" initials="D." surname="Bogdanovic">
    <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
    <address>
      <email>deanb@juniper.net</email>
    </address>
  </author>

    <author fullname="Benoit Claise" initials="B." surname="Claise">
    <organization>Cisco Systmes, Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <email>bclaise@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date day="05" month="March" year="2015" />

  <area>Operations and Management</area>
  <workgroup>NETMOD</workgroup>


  <abstract>
    <t>YANG became de facto standard language for data modeling in the industry.
   More and more groups uses YANG to create protocol and service models, both for
   configuration and operational models.  Currently there is a lack of consistent
   terminology to categorize those models. A consistent terminology would help models
   categorization, assist in the analysis the YANG data modeling effort in the IETF
   and in the industry, and facilitate the YANG-related discussions between different
   groups.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section anchor="open" title="Open Issues">
    <t><list style="empty">
      <t>The Acronyms list is not specific to this document. Candidate for removal?</t>
      <t>This is something I don't have experience with. As long we explain them
       in the document, I'm fine with removing the acronym section</t>
	    <t>We should discuss "service component YANG data models". I wonder if it doesn't
	      complicate things.</t>
      <t>I view them as Lego blocks. Will provide lot reasons to keep it in :-)</t>
	    <t>Complete the definitions</t>
      <t>I just tried to do that, to realize that was writing again longer
       description as in the text below. I think that mentioning them as layers
       is enough and then description of them is coming further down in the text.
       I rather use description then definition</t>
	    <t>Number the figures</t>
	    <t>Some "to do" in the draft itself</t>
	    <t>The "Second Dimension: Model Type" still has some inconsistencies</t>
	    <t>Standard extension YANG model: the deviation is not really an extension</t>
	   </list>
    </t>
  </section> <!-- open -->

  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
    <t>
    </t>
  </section> <!-- intro -->

  <section anchor="problem" title="Problem Statement">
    <t>YANG <xref target="RFC6020"/> became de-facto standard language for data modeling in the
	industry. Not only at the IETF, but also in multiple Standard Development Organizations,
	different consortia, ad hoc groups, and OSP. Therefore, many YANG models are being developed
	and published. Today, there is no classification of models, there are no clear guidelines on
	how to layer models on each other, or how to classify existing or new models.
	With this document, the authors are proposing a new way for YANG model classifications.</t>

   <t>Acknowledging that the YANG became the de-facto standard language for data modeling,
   the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) has been encouraging the working groups to use
   the NETCONF <xref target="RFC6241"/> and YANG standards for configuration, especially in new
   charters <xref target="Writable-MIB-Module-IESG-Statement"/>.</t>

   <t>YANG Models can classified according to two dimensions: based on the layer in the
   hierarchy of models, and based on the model type. Those two categories are covered in the
   next two sections.</t>

  </section> <!-- problem -->

  <section anchor="firstdimension" title="First Dimension: Network YANG Data Model Layering">
    <t>When developing models, there are two approaches possible, top down and
	   bottom up. Top down approach is driven by business requirements and bottom
	   up is driven by technological ones.
    </t>

	  <t>There are no hard requirements on how to create modeling, but it would be
	   useful to have a classification and to create models that can be easily reused,
	   as with this time and energy will be saved in future development. We should
	   stimulate both development styles, bottom up and top down, as each has its
	   benefits and groups to which a certain style will be more appealing than the
	   other.
    </t>
	  <t>For layering purposes, we can classify data models into four layers:</t>
	   <t>
       <list style="empty">
         <t>Business Service YANG Model </t>
		     <t>Network Service YANG Model </t>
		     <t>Service Component YANG Model </t>
		     <t>Protocol/Feature YANG Model </t>
	      </list>
      </t>

	   <t>Figure 1 displays example YANG models at different layers. By layering
       the models, it is easier to achieve reusability of existing lower layer
       models in higher level models and preventing duplication of same features
       modeled in different layers. When developing models per layers, it allows
       creating very focused groups in specific areas. As example, creating
       protocol model in protocol/feature YANG data models should involve people
       that have intimate experience of implemention details. On the other hand,
       network service models are best developed by people experienced in network
       operations. Same network service, can be implemented and modeled using
       different protocol and feature YANG models.
	  </t>

	<figure align="center">
	   <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

	business service (YANG) data models ----------------------------
	                 +-----------------------+
		               |                       |
		               |    metro ethernet     |
		               |       service         |
		               |                       |
		               +-----------------------+

	network service YANG data models -------------------------------

	         +------------+      +-------------+
	         |            |      |             |
	         |  VPWS      |      |   VPLS      |
	         |  L2VPN     |      |   L2VPN     |
	         |            |      |             |
	         +------------+      +-------------+

	service component YANG data models -----------------------------

	   +--------------+    +-------------+   +------------+
	   |  Service     |    |             |   |            |
	   |  Interface   |    |     LDP     |   |   iBGP     |
	   |              |    |             |   |            |
	   +--------------+    +-------------+   +------------+

	protocol/feature YANG data models ---------------------------------

	+------------+    +------------+   +--------------+  +-----------+
	|            |    |            |   |              |  |           |
	|     MPLS   |    |    BGP     |   |  Interface   |  |  Routing  |
	|            |    |            |   |              |  |           |
	+------------+    +------------+   +--------------+  +-----------+

	]]></artwork>
		</figure> <!-- YANG model layers -->

  <section anchor="business" title="Business service (YANG) model">
      <t>Business service models are the top level and are very customer specific.
        Vendors don't know what is important to the carrier from OSS perspective.
        That is known to the network operator and their customer specific use
        cases. Business service developer can create a very high level model,
        for example:
        customer LAN service
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
          container customer {
            description “adding metro LAN customers”
            leaf customer-name{
              description "virtual LAN customer name";
              type string;
            }
            leaf interface-name{
              description “metro LAN customer interface”
              type interface-name;
            }
            leaf site-name{
              description “customer site name";
              type string;
            }
          }]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>The model above is a simple business model. It can be exposed to
        external applications that can very electively create a new service.
        The application developer doesn't have to know the underlying
        technology used, as it potentially would have no meaning if exposed as
        network service YANG model name VPLS L2VPN. The network service YANG
        model might have some parameters that would have no meaning to the end
        developer, like route-distiguisher, vrf-target, instance-type. These
        parameters can be very effectively hidden from the high level business
	      service API consumer.</t>

      <t>Some different Standard Development Organizations" have different
        naming conventions for Business Service Models. For example, the Metro
        Ethernet Forum (MEF) definition of a service co-incides with a "business
        service" in this document, i.e., it is defined by the set of parameters
        that are agreed between the Subscriber and the SP (in the case of retail
        services) or between an Operator and the SP (in the case of wholesale
        services). This paragraph from the scope of MEF 10.3 (Ethernet Services
        Attributes) illustrates this point:
        "This document describes Ethernet Service attributes for services
        provided to the Subscriber by the Service Provider.  The Ethernet
        Services are modeled from the point of view of the Subscriber’s
        equipment referred to as the Customer Edge (CE) that is used to access
        the service. The basic elements of Ethernet Services are defined. In
        addition, a number of Service Attributes are defined that may be offered
        as part of an Ethernet Service including the definition of Service
        Level Specification."
	     </t>

	     <t>There is also this from MEF 26.1, regarding operator (i.e. wholesale)
         services:
	       "This document uses the following Service Model. For a given EVC, the
         Subscriber contracts with a Service Provider to be responsible for
         delivering Ethernet Services among the UNIs in the EVC.  The Service
         Provider, in turn, selects and contracts with various MEN Operators
	       to deliver the UNI-to-UNI services.  It is the responsibility of the
         Service Provider to ensure that the appropriate service and interface
         attribute values from each Operator are such that the UNI to UNI
         service features purchased by the Subscriber can be delivered."
	      </t>

	      <t>Note that business service models might be written in a different
          language than YANG.</t>
  </section> <!-- business -->


  <section anchor="networkService" title="Network Service YANG Data Model">
      <t>Network service YANG models are created by network operators
        when they choose how to configure their network from technology point of
        view. They decide which technology is best match for their business
        needs and based on that create network service data models. With more and
        more configuration models being available, both vendor and standards one,
        network service model developer can create reusable components based on
        the configuration models, and use those service components data models to
        create end to end service model.</t>

	    <t>For example, http://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-l3vpn-service-yang/
        provides an abstracted view of the Layer 3 IPVPN service configuration
        components. It will be up to a management system to take this as an
        input and use specific configurations models to configure the different
        network elements to deliver the service.
      </t>

	     <t>Network service data models can be developed in multiple ways.
         Building them monolithic from vendor models or by combining one or more
         service components into an end to end service data model. It specifies
         complete service that is provided by the network operator.
         Building monolithic network service model has an advantage of doing it
         fast, but at the expense of flexibility of updating the service later
         or switching vendors. Such an end to end service can be VPLS/VPWS
         L2VPN, IPsec, etc. If we take into example VPLS L2VPN service, it can
         be built as a single network service model or it can be built from
         several service components. VPWS L2VPN service can be built on top of
         MPLS or IP network core. When building such a network service model,
         network variations have to be taken into the account and by creating
         service components modle, such as MPLS, BGP service component models,
         it is easier to build a network service model, such as VPWS L2VPN.</t>
      </section> <!-- networkService -->

	  <section anchor="component" title="Service Component YANG Data Model">
        <t>Service component is specific way how operator is using configuration
          options in the data model to create part of a service. Such example
          can be iBGP. Full BGP configuration model is available as vendor and
          standard models, but service model developer has a choice to create
          iBGP as separate service component that can be reused in other models.
          There can be multiple iBGP service component models, as not all
          service model developers have to use same abstraction, and it can be
          helpful to have multiple models developed that cover different use
          cases.
        </t>
   </section> <!-- component -->

   <section anchor="protocol" title="Protocol/Feature YANG data models">
        <t>This is base model for all higher models. It fully describes
          protocol, such as OSPF <xref target='I-D.yeung-netmod-ospf'/>,
          ISIS <xref target='I-D.ietf-isis-yang-isis-cfg'/> or feature,
          exapmle access control list <xref target='I-D.ietf-netmod-acl-model'/>.
          The base model can be either vendor specific, which then describes
          vendor implementation of the protocol or feature or standard model. Key
          difference between those two is what is implemented. Vendor device model
          will always describe what is implmented, which can more or even less
          then in standard model. Standard model describes what is agreed in the
          industry to be accepted as base description.
        </t>
   </section> <!-- protocol/feature YANG data models -->
 </section> <!-- firstdimension -->

 <section title="Second Dimension: Model Type">
	  <t>At very high level, models can be divided into proprietary and standard.
      Each vendor, consortium, open source project can publish their models and
      those are considered proprietary models. When an SDO, such as IETF or ITU,
      publishes an accepted model document, then this is a standard model. There
      are use cases where a consortium has published work which de facto became
      standard, such as Linux kernel, but for the clarity in this document,
      authors are making a separation between models based on the above
      description.
    </t>
	  <t><list style="empty">

		<t>Standard YANG Model: </t>

		<t>Standard Extension YANG Model: .</t>

		<t>Proprietary Extension to Standard YANG Model: As the Standard YANG Models contains
		a subset of all the Vendor Configuration Models, proprietary extensions must complement
		the Standard YANG Models to represent a Vendor Configuration Model.</t>

		<t>Vendor Configuration Model: It describes all configurable capabilities of the
		device and what device vendor exposes for configuration. The vendor configuration model
		can be CLI or YANG-based.</t>

		<t>Proprietary YANG Model: A non Standard YANG Model. </t>

	   </list></t>

	   <t>As mentioned earlier in this document, there are two ways of designing
		  models, top down and bottom up with one restriction. Everything is dependent
		  on the vendor data model. That model describes all the possibilities and if
		  model developers prefers, they can use vendor model only to design service
		  components, network service and business service. Using vendor model provides
		  all capabilities today, but it comes with restrictions of portability between
		  vendors and to certain extent devices.
		  On the other hand, only standard models and standard extensions can be used,
		  but this might result in less feature rich or less efficient services.
		  Service model developer has a choice to reuse service components or write
		  a model completely based on vendor data model.
		</t>

		<t>TO DO: I don't understand this paragraph above.
		</t>
    <t>We should discuss this</t>

       <section anchor="standard" title="Standard YANG model">
          <t>With YANG we have a common language, that enables different
          communities to express data models that are widely understandable
          without lot of additional explanation. This enables different groups,
          such as IETF, to standardize data models, defined as an IETF RFC,
          and vendors to support them, which will make it easier to for network
          operators to manage their network configuration programmatically.
          For example,
          A YANG Data Model for Interface Management <xref target="RFC7223"/>,
          or the Configuration Data Model for the IP Flow Information Export
          (IPFIX) and Packet Sampling (PSAMP) Protocols <xref target="RFC6728"/>.
          </t>
       </section> <!-- standard -->

       <section anchor="standardextension" title="Standard Extension YANG Model">
          <t>Standard Extension is a the conditional portion of a Standard YANG
            Model, expressed with the feature, if-feature, augment YANG
            statements <xref target="RFC6020"/>. An example of such standard
            extension is policy based routing (PBR). PBR is found in many vendor
            implementations and have many common features, but not all vendors
            support PBR on all of their devices.
		      </t>
       </section> <!-- standardextension -->

	   <section anchor="proprietaryextensiontostandard" title="Proprietary Extension to Standard YANG Model">
       <t>Proprietary extension is a conditional portion of a Standard YANG
         Model, expressed with feature, if-feature, augment YANG statements
         <xref target="RFC6020"/>. Proprietary extension can be a feature
         depending on harward platform capabilities and it is not available by
         other vendors. Such an example could be match condition for packet
         classification used for PBR.
		   </t>
     </section> <!-- proprietaryextensiontostandard -->

     <section anchor="vendor" title="Vendor configuration model">
       <t>Base model for all other models is the vendor configuration model.
         It describes all configurable capabalities of the device and what
         device vendor exposes for configuration.</t>

	      <t>The standard configuration model is a subset of vendor configuration
	      model. The standard configuration model can be broken into base model
	      and standard extension models, where the base is common data model and
	      standard extensions are standard features that are not implemented
		    by all vendors. Example of standard base model is Access
	      Control List and routing filter is a standard extension on ACL. Or
	      another example: encryption algorithm is standard feature, but the
	      different types, like md5, hmac-md5, hmac-sha1, etc are standard
	      extensions, as it is not that all vendors have all encryption
	      algorithm types implemented.</t>

		  <t>Although all vendors provide very similar functionality using
        standards, implementations are different. One of basic examples are
        dynamic routing protocols. We can see today two main types of routing
        protocol configuration.
        </t>
        <t><list style="empty">
          <t>protocol centric -  all the protocol related config is contained
            with the protocol itself. Especially in case of multiple instances
            of the routing protocol running in different routing-instances
            (routing-instance as described in core routing model <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-routing-cfg"/>),
            all the routing-instance protocol config is contained in the
            default routing instance.
          </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            Router ospf 10
            Default-metric 100
            Address-family ipv4 vrf VRF1
                Network x.x.x.x area 0

            Address-family ipv4 vrf VRF2
                Network x.x.x.x area 0

            Address-family ipv4
                Network x.x.x.x area 1
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t><list style="empty">
          <t>In term of YANG model, the routing protocol configuration will be
            defined within the default routing-instance and the routing-protocol
            config will contain multiple instances referring to other
            routing-instances.
          </t>
          <t>VRF centric - All the protocol related config for a routing-instance
            is contained within this routing-instance.
          </t>
        </list></t>
        <figure>
            <artwork>
            Routing-instance VRF1 {
              Protocols isis {

              }
            }
            Routing-instance VRF2 {
              Protocols isis {

              }
            }
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          <t><list style="empty">
            <t>In term of YANG model, the routing protocol configuration for a
              routing-instance will be defined within the associated
              routing-instance.
            </t>

			 <t>The bottom line message is that, even if YANG models are standardized,
			 they will provide different CLI outcomes, simply because the CLI among
			 vendors is not standardized.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section> <!--vendor -->

	  <section anchor="proprietary" title="Proprietary YANG Model">
          <t>While waiting for the Standard YANG Models to be published,
            the different vendors might offer Proprietary YANG Models.
          </t>
      </section> <!-- proprietary -->

  </section> <!-- Second Dimension -->

  <section title="Typical Architecture">
    <figure>
      <artwork>


        +--------------------------------------------------------+
        | Application                                            |
        |   +------------------------------------------------+   |
        |   |business service model                          |   |
        |   +------------------------------------------------+   |
        +--------------------------------------------------------+


        +--------------------------------------------------------+
        | Controller                                             |
        |   +------------------------------------------------+   |
        |   |network service model                           |   |
        |   | +-------------------+   +-------------------+  |   |
        |   | | Service Component |   | Service Component |  |   |
        |   | | Model             |   | Model             |  |   |
        |   | |                   |   |                   |  |   |
        |   | +-------------------+   +-------------------+  |   |
        |   +------------------------------------------------+   |
		    +--------------------------------------------------------+

		    +--------------------------------------------------------+
        | Network element                                        |
        |                             |                          |
        |  +-----------------------+  |  +-------------------+   |
        |  | Standard YANG model   |  |  |   Proprietary     |   |
        |  |                       |  |  |   YANG model      |   |
		    |  +-----------------------+  |  |                   |   |
        |                             |  |                   |   |
        |  +-----------------------+  |  |                   |   |
        |  | Proprietary Extension |  |  |                   |   |
        |  | To YANG Standard      |  |  |                   |   |
        |  | Model                 |  |  |                   |   |
        |  +-----------------------+  |  +-------------------+   |
        |                             |                          |
        |  +-------------------------------------------------+   |
        |  |          Vendor Configuration Model             |   |
        |  +-------------------------------------------------+   |
        +--------------------------------------------------------+

      </artwork>
    </figure>

	<figure>
      <artwork>

      Business Sbervices (YANG) Data Models
             |                    |
      -----------------------------------
      |           Applications           |
      -----------------------------------
             |     \              |
             |        \           |      ------- Network Service YANG
             |           \        |              Data Models
             |              \     |
             |                 \  |
       -------------         --------------       mapping between the
      |             |       |             |  ---  Network Service YANG
      | Controller  |       | Controller  |       data model, and the network
      |             |       |             |       topology YANG model
      ---------------        -------------
         |   |   |             |   |   |
         |   |   |             |   |   | ------- protocol/feature
         |   |   |             |   |   |          YANG data models
         |   |   |             |   |   |
        NE1 NE2 NEn           NE1 NE2 NEn  ------- Network Elements

      </artwork>
    </figure>

	 <t>TO DO: need some more explanation.
	 </t>
  </section> <!-- Typical Architecture -->

  <section title="IETF, Other SDOs, and Opensource">
	 <t>IETF, as a SDO, is really well positioned to standardize protocol/feature
	 YANG models. With a wide range of expertise found within its WGs focused on
	 those technology definitions. As IETF participants implement those protocols,
	 they have deep expertise about the implementation and finding a common
	 base standard configuration model between vendors should be a very
	 viable goal.
	 </t>

   <t>In some situation where the protocols are standardized by different SDOs,
	 those SDOs should be responsible for its YANG data modeling effort.
	 For example, the IETF has transferred the responsibility for some IEEE
	 technology-related MIB modules to the IEEE 802.1 and 802.3 Working Group
	 <xref target="RFC4663"/>, <xref target="RFC7448"/>. Similarly, the IEEE
	 should be responsible for similar YANG data modeling efforts.
	 </t>
   <t>Although many network operators participate in IETF work, developing
   higher level models requires network operations expertise. If such teams
   within right WG can be formed, then some service models can be developed
   within IETF, but some groups, like CableLabs, NANOG, could be better
   positioned for service modeling.</t>
   <t>Today there are many open source projects and some of them are becoming
     de facto standards, like Linux kernel. Many such open source projecs, like
     Open Daylight, Openstack, Openconfig, etc, are doing very good work and
     their work is being accepted and deployed in production environments.
     They bring lot of very valuable experience to other groups. From IETF
     perspective, if there is such a work present, it can be used as a very good
     starting point for modeling within IETF.
   </t>

  </section> <!-- IETF, Other SDOs, Opensource -->

  <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>At this stage, authors of the draft didn't look into security considerations.</t>
  </section> <!-- security -->

  <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>This document requests no action by IANA. </t>
  </section> <!-- iana -->

  <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>Thanks to David Ball for his enlightenments on Metro Ethernet Forum service aspects.</t>
  </section> <!-- ack -->

  <section anchor ="changes" title="Change log [RFC Editor: Please remove]">
    <t>version 1: restructure the document, add the two dimensions, add the interaction with the different
	SDOs and opensource projects, add the definitions.</t>
    </section> <!-- changes -->
  </middle>

  <back>
	    <references title="Normative References">
		  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6020'?>
	   </references>
	   <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4663'?>
		  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6241'?>
		  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6242'?>
		  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6536'?>
		  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6728'?>
		  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7223'?>
		  <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7448'?>
		  <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-routing-cfg'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-isis-yang-isis-cfg'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-acl-model'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.yeung-netmod-ospf'?>
	    <reference anchor="Writable-MIB-Module-IESG-Statement" target="https://www.ietf.org/iesg/statement/writable-mib-module.html">
            <front>
              <title>Writable MIB Module IESG Statement</title>
              <author/>
              <date/>
            </front>
           </reference>
	  </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
